General Cartoon Collection
General Cartoon Collection
1870-1995
1930-1949
Syracuse University. Library. Special Collections Research Center.
3 linear ft.
Original newspaper comic strip and comics cartoons, editorial cartoons and magazine cartoons/illustrations representative of the history of cartooning from the late 19th century to 1963; with some material from the 1990s.
2670148
Biographical History
The General Cartoon Collection is an artificial collection bringing together samples of original work from a wide variety of cartoonists and illustrators.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The General Cartoon Collection contains original newspaper comic strip and comics cartoons, editorial cartoons and magazine cartoons/illustrations representative of the history of cartooning from the late 19th century to the late-1950s. Artists represented include Herblock, C. K. Berryman, Billy DeBeck, Bernhard Gillam, Eugene "Zim" Zimmerman, Winsor McCay, T. E. Powers, Alex Raymond and many others. There are also unidentified cartoonists or unidentified art featured in this collection, including items related to Looney Tunes, Pepsi-cola and Superman.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items were sorted into 3 containers (based on size). Cartoons in each container are in alphabetical order by artist name.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
A number of cartoons were separated into standalone collections, or transferred into existing collections, for example items from C.D. Batchelor, George Herriman, Carey Orr and others.
Other Related Finding Aids
A partial set of cards containing titles, dates, captions, condition and other information about some of the cartoons is located in the finding aids folder. It appears to have been completed after receiving the collection, possibly by a staff member, student or intern.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Anderson, Jesse Sylvester, 1873-1966.; Bairnsfather, Bruce, 1887-1959.; Bastian, Robert O.; Berryman, Clifford Kennedy, 1869-1949.; Block, Herbert, 1909-2001.; Gillam, Bernhard, 1856-1896.; Peb, 1926-; Swan, Curt.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Illustrators -- United States.; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Illustrations.; Cartoonists.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Majority purchased from Goodspeed's Bookshop, 1963.
Vet Anderson artwork (2 items), purchased, 2012.
Inventory
- Cartoons
  - Anderson, Vet (Jesse Sylvester)
    - "Prepare a pathetic, heart-interest recitation—how the cow has gone dry and the horse halt, then having your tears on tap, turn 'em on", undated; pen and ink on illustration board; 24" x 18" (Oversize 2)
    - "He speaks of masters. I know none.", undated; pen and ink on illustration board; 19.5" x 14.25" (Oversize 2)
  - Bairnsfather, Bruce
    - Untitled, undated; original artwork; watercolor, paint and white pencil on pasteboard; 14 ½'' x 21'' (Oversize 2)
  - Bastian, Robert
    - Untitled, JFK and inflation, 1961-1963; cartoon; charcoal and ink on paper; 14" x 17" (Oversize 1)
  - Bateman, H. M.
    - "The Chief's Eyes!", Punch, 27 Dec 1924; magazine illustration; pen and ink on illustration board; 11" x 16" (Oversize 1)
  - Belloc, Piere (Peb)
    - "Now Look What You Made Him Do!", Annenberg Syndicate, 1963; editorial cartoon; signed by Peb; 11'' x 14'' (Oversize 1)
    - "Stand, Cowards! Be Not So Base As to Fly Before A Single Knight, Who Dares Encounter You All!", Annenberg Syndicate, 1963; editorial cartoon; signed by Peb; 11'' x 14'' (Oversize 1)
  - Berdanier, Paul Frederick
    - "Where Does He Go From Here?", 8 June 1940; political cartoon; signed by Paul Berdanier; crayon, pen and ink onillustration board; 13'' x 22'' (Oversize 2)
  - Berndt, Walter
    - "Little Herby", 28 Oct 1931; comic strip daily; signed by Walter Berndt; pen and ink onillustration board; 6 ½'' x 20'' (Oversize 2)
  - Berryman, C. K. (Clifford K.)
    - "Chamberlain Says He Knows the Mine Secret", Washington EveningStar, Feb 1940; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed by C. K. Berryman; pen andink on illustration board; 13 ½'' x 14 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
    - "Headline Makers—But Not in Print!", Washington Evening Star, 31 Dec 1939; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed as Jim Berryman; pen and inkon illustration board; 13 ½'' x 14 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
  - Black, Oz
    - "Here in Lincoln", Sunday Journal & Star, 11 Feb 1940; original drawing; inscribed and signed by Oz Black; 22 ½'' x 23''; Newspaper clipping of cartoon also found in Box 3. (Oversize 3)
  - Block, Herb, See Herblock.
  - Bradley, Luther
    - "The Queen of May", Chicago Daily News, 1 May 1907; editorial cartoon; signed by Luther Bradley; pen and ink onillustration board; 14'' x 15'' (Oversize 1)
  - Bradley and Edgington
    - "Rex Morgan, M.D." [?], 7 Jul 1949; comic strip daily; pen and ink on illustration board; 21'' x 8'' (Oversize 2)
  - Breger, Irv
    - "All right, I'll tell you why I left my last book-keeping job—but you tell me why your book-keeper left this one!", undated; magazine illustration; watercolor; pen and ink on illustrationboard; 9 ½'' x 11 ½'' (Oversize 1)
  - Briggs
    - "The Talkative Golfer", undated; sketch; signed by Briggs; pen and ink on illustrationboard; 13'' x 17'' (Oversize 2)
  - Brown, Edward Scott (T. Brown)
    - "The Haunted House", New York Herald Tribune, undated; political cartoon; signed by Brown; pen and ink on illustrationboard; 14'' x 17'' (Oversize 2)
  - Bush, C. G.
    - "Another Proof of Dreyfus' Innocence", circa 1899; political cartoon; signed by C.G. Bush; graphite, pen and ink onillustration board; 19'' x 22'' (Oversize 3)
  - Cassell, John
    - "Untitled [man in top hat and ragamuffins]", 1890-1910; original drawing; opaque white, brush, pen and ink on illustrationboard; 21 ¾'' x 18 ¼'' (Oversize 3)
  - Caniff, Milton
    - "Steve Canyon", 26 Sep 1956; comic strip daily; inscribed and signed by Milt Caniff; opaquewhite, brush, pen and ink on illustration board; 7 ¼'' x 22 ¾'' (Oversize 2)
  - Chubb
    - "After Thirteen Years", 1931; political cartoon; signed by Chubb; pen and ink on illustrationboard; 14 ¾'' x 19'' (Oversize 2)
  - Collier, Nate
    - "Hey! Take Your HandOff!", 1941; editorial cartoon; graphite, crayon and ink on illustrationboard; 10'' x 12'' (Oversize 1)
  - Conselman, Bill & Plumb, Charlie
    - "Ella Cinders", United FeatureSyndicate, 9 Sep 1938; comic strip daily; ink and pen on illustration board; 5 ¾'' x 22'' (Oversize 2)
  - Davenport, Homer Calvin
    - "The Food Trust", circa 1900; editorial cartoon; ink and pen on paper; 25'' x 30½'' (Map-case 107)
  - DeBeck, Billy
    - "Barney Google", 17 Feb (after 1922); comic strip daily; traces of graphite, blue pencil, pen and ink onillustration board; 4 ¾'' x 17 ¾'' (Oversize 2)
  - Donahey, William
    - "Pay Day! Yeah?", Cleveland-Plain Dealer, undated; political cartoon; ink and pen on illustration board; 13'' x 18'' (Oversize 2)
  - Ehrhart
    - Untitled, tramp and lady, 9 Jun 1893; original drawing; ink and pen on illustration board; 15 ¼'' x 15 ¼'' (Oversize 2)
  - Forrest, Hal
    - "Tailspin Tommy,"Bell Syndicate, 1930; comic strip daily; pen and ink on illustration board; 2 cartoons; 7 ¼ '' x 23'' (Oversize 2)
  - Foster, R.
    - "He had to do it!!", 19; 40; political cartoon; traces of graphite, blue pencil, pen and ink onillustration board; 11'' x 14'' (Oversize 1)
  - Gillam, Bernhard
    - "Hubbell's Work", circa 1880; political cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; drawing ismatted; 7 ¼'' x 8'' (Oversize 1)
    - [Mahdist rebellion], Puck, 1884 or 1885; political cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 6 ¾'' x 9'' (Oversize 1)
  - Glackens, L. M.
    - "In the Republican Dark-Room, An Amateur Photographer Who Spoils Good Plates by Using Bad Chemicals," Puck, 1910; political cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 16 ¼ '' x 20'' (Oversize 2)
      March 2 1910 edition of Puck is also in Box 2.
  - Grissinger, Harry
    - "Miss Parker cleared her throat,'You don't need to lie, Mr. Briggs,' she said sternly.", undated; original drawing; inscribed and signed by Grissinger; traces ofgraphite, watercolor and ink on illustration board; 17 ¾'' x 20'' (Oversize 3)
  - Haney, R. T.
    - "The Broken Pledge", 24 Jun 1940; editorial cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 14 ½'' x 18 ½'' (Oversize 2)
  - Hanny, William
    - "A Little Road Information", undated; editorial cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 14'' x 17 ½'' (Oversize 2)
  - Harman, Fred
    - "Red Ryder", 31 Oct 1939; comic strip daily; pen and ink on illustration board; 6 ¼'' x 22'' (Oversize 2)
  - Hayes, Geoff
    - "Best Wishes!" from characters Juneand Ted, Bell Syndicate, undated; comic strip; pen and ink on illustration board; 5 ¼'' x 20'' (Oversize 2)
  - Henderson
    - "Spring Design,"Sunday Journal, undated; editorial cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 14 ½'' x 17'' (Oversize 2)
  - Herblock
    - "This would beat the Bonneville Dam Ceremony", 1937; editorial cartoon; graphite and ink on illustration board; 14'' x 17'' (Oversize 2)
  - Howard, Oscar
    - "Untitled [tavern girl], "New York Daily News[?], 1932; illustration; crayon, pen and ink on illustration board; 14'' x 17'' (Oversize 2)
  - Johnson, Charles Howard
    - "St. Valentine Number,"Life magazine cover, circa 1893; original drawing; traces if graphite, watercolor and ink onillustration board; 20'' x 25 ½'' (Oversize 3)
  - Johnson, Vic
    - McGovern / Vietnam cartoon, original drawing; editorial cartoon; chalk on paper (Oversize 1)
  - Johnston, Earl S.
    - "He Seems to Be in Earnest Now,"Arkansas Democrat[?], 1930s; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed by Earle S. Johnston; tracesof graphite, crayon, pen and ink on illustration board; 11'' x 15 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
  - Keys, Larry
    - "The Same Old Snipe Hunt", undated; editorial cartoon; traces of graphite, crayon and ink on illustrationboard; 19 ¼'' x 22'' (Oversize 3)
  - Larimer, Harry
    - "The Greeting She Would Like Most to Receive,"News-Sentinel, 1940; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed by Harry Larimer; pen and inkon illustration board; 14'' x 17 ½'' (Oversize 2)
  - Lehti, John
    - "Tales from the Great Book, Noah's Ark", 26 May; original cartoon; inscribed and signed by Lehti; pen and ink onillustration board; 14'' x 17 ½'' (Oversize 3)
  - Lewis, R. A.
    - "I Am Monarch of All That I Survey,"Milwaukee Journal, 1930s; editorial cartoon; traces of graphite, opaque white, crayon, pen andink on illustration board; 11'' x 14 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
    - "Victory in Spain,"Milwaukee Journal, 1939; editorial cartoon; traces of graphite, opaque white, crayon, pen andink on illustration board; 11'' x 14 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
  - Loring, Paul
    - "You May Need a Round Trip Ticket, Big Boy,"Providence Evening Bulletin, circa 1939; editorial cartoon; blue pencil, opaque white, brush, pen and ink onillustration board; 13'' x 13'' (Oversize 1)
  - Lubbers, Bob
    - Long Sam, 8 Mar 1957; comic strip daily; inscribed and signed by BobLubbers; pen and ink on illustration board; 6 ½'' x 20 ¾'' (Oversize 2)
  - Maier, Carl
    - Untitled, three sketches for comic feature, undated; signed by Maier; graphite, pen and ink on illustrationboard; 17 ¾'' x 21 ½'' (Oversize 2)
  - Maxwell, Gee Tee (George T.)
    - "But, Gosh-h-h, Who's Gonna Pay for 'Em?", late 1930s; editorial cartoon; crayon, pen and ink on illustrationboard; 14 ½'' x 17 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
    - "Pruning Time", 1940; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed by Gee Tee Maxwell;crayon, pen and ink on illustration board; 11'' x 11 ½'' (Oversize 1)
    - "Why Of Course It's Not Political!", 1940; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed by Gee Tee Maxwell; crayon,opaque white, pen and ink on illustration board; 11'' x 11 ½'' (Oversize 1)
  - McCarthy, Father Justin
    - Brother Sebastian panel, 1957; comic panel; watercolor and ink on illustration board; matted; 7'' x 8''; Series ran in Friar magazine and was syndicated until 1986. (Oversize 1)
  - McCay, Winsor
    - Untitled, multiple dwellings bill, undated; editorial cartoon; graphite, pen and ink on illustration board; matted; 9'' x 17 ¼'' (Oversize 2)
  - Nelan, Charles
    - Untitled, "Beware of...", circa 1870; political cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 18 ½'' x 17 ½'' (Oversize 3)
  - Nofziger, Ed
    - Untitled, crane with neck tied in knot, 14 Jun 1939; Magazine illustration; inscribed and signed by Ed Nofziger;watercolor, pen and ink on illustration board; 7 ½'' x 17'' (Oversize 2)
      Probably appeared in the Saturday Evening Post.
  - Nor, E.
    - Untitled, small snake wringing neck of large snake, undated; original comic cartoon; watercolor and ink on illustration board; 7 ½'' x 17'' (Oversize 2)
  - Packer, Fred
    - The Winnah, 1940; editorial cartoon; crayon, opaque white, pen and ink on illustrationboard; 14 ¾'' x 18'' (Oversize 2)
  - Page, Grover
    - The Trail Blazer and the Blaze Trailer, Courier Journal, Louisville, Kentucky, 10 Jul 1932; editorial cartoon; crayon on illustration board; 15'' x 20'' (Oversize 2)
  - Patzer, George L.
    - Next?, 1940; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed by Patzer; pen and ink onillustration board; 15'' x 20'' (Oversize 2)
  - Pease, Lucius Curtis (Lute Pease)
    - "Plain Evidence,"Newark Evening News, circa 1934; editorial cartoon; crayon, opaque white, pen and ink on illustrationboard; 11 ¼'' x 14 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
  - Powers, T. E.
    - "What Have You Got for Tomorrow's Paper?," New York Journal, circa 1918; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed by T.E. Powers; pen and inkon illustration board; 9 ½'' x 11 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
      Reprinted in The New York Daily News, March 23, 1941. Newspaper version alsoin Box 1.
  - Pratt, Newton
    - "Valor Is Not Enough,"Sacramento Bee, circa 1939; editorial cartoon; traces of graphite, opaque white, crayon, pen andink on illustration board; 11 ¼'' x 15'' (Oversize 1)
  - Pughe, J. S.
    - "International Commercial Race," Puck, 9 Jul 1894; political cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 11 ½'' x 11 ½'' (Oversize 1)
  - Raymond, Alex
    - Jungle Jim, 17 Jul 1938; panel cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 25 ¼'' x 12 ¼'' (Oversize 3)
  - Rosol, John
    - Here and There, 1941; several daily strips on newsprint, both sides; possibly a galley proof; 24'' x 16'' (Oversize 3)
  - Satterfield, Robert W.
    - The Killjoy, early 20th century; illustration; pen and ink on illustration board; 13'' x 15 ½'' (Oversize 1)
  - Shaw, Dick
    - "I'm worried! That circus train shouldda been by here fifteen minutes ago!", Saturday Evening Post, undated; magazine illustration; traces of graphite, opaque white, pen and inkon illustration board; includes clipping of printed version; 9 ½'' x 12 ¼'' (Oversize 1)
  - Shoemaker, Vaughn
    - "Now Beware of the Trojan Market Basket", 1942; editorial cartoon; inscribed and signed by Shoemaker; traces of graphite, opaque white, pen and ink on illustration board; 16 ¾'' x 20'' (Oversize 2)
  - Smith, Dorman H.
    - "Front Seat - In a position to lead the parade", 1940s; editorial cartoon; traces of graphite, crayon, opaque white and ink; 11 ¼'' x 28'' (Oversize 3)
    - "Nanny Grabbing - A little fun in Washington", 1940s; editorial cartoon; traces of graphite, crayon, opaque white and ink; 11 ¼'' x 28'' (Oversize 3)
  - Summers, William Henry
    - "Chute Brigade Over Philadelphia,"The Cleveland News, 22 Jun 1940; editorial cartoon; crayon, blue, opaque white and ink on illustrationboard; 22 ½'' x 28'' (Oversize 3)
    - "Il Duce Jumps In,"The Cleveland News, Jun 1940; editorial cartoon; crayon, blue, opaque white and ink on illustrationboard; 22 ½'' x 28'' (Oversize 3)
  - Swan, Curt
    - Untitled Superman panel, Action Comics/DC National Comics, undated; panel comic; #325; pen and ink on illustration board; 13'' x 21'' (Oversize 2)
  - Taylor, R.
    - "Port of Nassau, Bahamas", 1979; reproduction, signed and inscribed "to Richard 3/19/79" (Oversize 2)
  - Taylor, Walter
    - "Why, Darling, can't you guess?", The New Yorker, undated; comic cartoon; watercolor, pen and ink on illustration board; matted; 7 ¼'' x 10'' (Oversize 2)
  - Victor
    - "The Gambling Mania: Uncle Sam in the hands of thieves," Judge, undated; magazine clipping; color illustration (Oversize 2)
  - Walker, Ryan
    - "The Laborer", 1910; original cartoon; graphite, pen and ink on illustration board; 12'' x 12'' (Oversize 2)
  - Webster, H. T. (Harold Tucker)
    - "Mgr. Selee's Real Difficulty Will Be to Retain His Pitchers", 1902-1905; sports cartoon; pen and ink on illustration board; 9'' x 14'' (Oversize 1)
  - Zimmerman, Eugene (Zim)
    - "The Diary of Dauntless Dick, The Hobo Hound", undated; panel cartoon for comic strip; traces of graphite, pen and ink on illustration board; 15'' x 22'' (Oversize 2)
  - Unidentified
    - Looney Tunes, Warner Brothers Cartoons, Inc., 11 Jun 1949; original cartoon featuring Bugs Bunny and Elmer Fudd; pen and ink on illustration board; 23'' x 8'' (Oversize 2)
    - Sketchbook, undated; spiral-bound sketchbook with a number of original ink drawings and cartoons; 9" x 11" (Box 1)
    - "The C Bells", undated; small pen-and-ink cartoon of man with top hat and monocle, large bell, surrounded by elves[?], signed with interlocked initials "PC" or "CP" (Box 1)
    - Untitled [Pepsi-cola], undated; comic strip; pen and ink on illustration board; 6'' x 18'' (Oversize 2)
    - Untitled [from Newspaper Enterprise Association Service], 6 Jul 1948; comic strip featuring characters Pug and Bertie; pen and ink onillustration board; 10'' x 12'' (Oversize 1)
- Printed material
  - Book, Blue Book, King Features Syndicate comics, 1946 (Oversize 3)
  - National Cartoonists Society, 26 Apr 1960; 23 Apr 1962; 14th Annual Reuben Awards pamphlet, 16th Annual Reuben Awards "year book" (Box 1)
  - Newsletter, Comic Art Studies, from Russel B. Nye Popular Culture Collection, 1993-1995; issues 50, 53, 54, 55 (Box 1)